Okay בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Okay, no ציומא. tziyuma.
Okay, so today's דף daf is כב. Chaf Bet. We pick up
on the bottom of כא עמוד ב Chaf Aleph Amud Bet and
we have just been dealing with the issue about שאילת שלום she'elas
shalom by an אבל, avel, and now we actually pick up to
a very central and important discussion about when the אבילות aveilus begins,
especially if there are different members of the family, and there's a
lot of contention around the specifics of this, but we're not going
to be dealing with the actual bottom-line הלכה. halacha. But let's take
a look. We are five lines from the bottom on כא עמוד
ב. Chaf Aleph Amud Bet. תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: אבל ג' ימים
הראשונים בא ממקום קרוב מונה עמהם בא ממקום רחוק מונה לעצמו. avel
gimmel yamim harishonim ba mimakom karov moneh imahem ba mimakom rachok moneh
le'atzmo. So somebody... here is what's powerful fundamentally about this idea is
the concept of אבילות aveilus as being observed by the family and
not just by the individual. So therefore it says that if somebody
comes within the first three days of the שבעה shiva and then
meets up with the rest of the family that is sitting שבעה,
shiva, he does not start on the day that he arrived and
the day that he found out, but rather
he integrates himself with their שבעה shiva and his שבעה shiva will
begin when they began. That's the language of מונה עמהם, moneh imahem,
he counts it with them from the seven days. בא ממקום רחוק,
Ba mimakom rachok, that's if he came from a faraway place, so
conceptually even though he wasn't present and maybe even if he hadn't
found out, if he wasn't even aware of it until that time,
but conceptually you view it as if they were all together because,
you know, they were nearby. Exactly the definition of nearby is not
clear. תוספות, Tosafot, if you'll take a look in one sentence, says
פירוש בהלכות גדולות דהיינו י' פרסאות, Peirush Behilchos Gedolos dehainu yud parsa'os,
ten parsa which is 40 מיל. mil.
A מיל mil is about a kilometer, so what does that translate
to? A kilometer's three-fifths of a mile, so what is that, about
25 miles? Okay. So, and that's probably based on the גמרא Gemara
that says that's distance that a person can travel in a day.
So conceptually you view it as if they were together. But if
it was from a faraway place, then he's on his own. מכאן
ואילך, Mikan ve'eilach, after the first three days, and this is again
reflecting the idea that three days is the עיקר אבילות, ikar aveilus,
the first three. After that, אפילו בא ממקום קרוב מונה לעצמו, afilu
ba mimakom karov moneh le'atzmo, then he's doing his own separate observance
because it doesn't incorporate with the fundamental beginning of the observance that
they were doing. רבי שמעון אומר אפילו בא ביום השביעי ממקום קרוב
מונה עמהם. Rabbi Shimon Omer afilu ba beyom hashevi'i mimakom karov moneh
imahem. Even on day seven he can be considered part of their
שבעה shiva and then he would only have done a few hours.
That's more of you're integrating into the family as opposed to the
תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma. I'm sorry? תנא קמא? Tanna Kamma? This seems
to be more that you're integrating.
Yeah, of course. Right, totally. אמר מר ג' ימים הראשונים בא ממקום
קרוב מונה עמהם. Amar Mar gimmel yamim harishonim ba mimakom karov moneh
imahem. אמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן והוא שיש גדול
הבית בבית. Amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan vihu she'ish
gadol habayis babayis. Now that also requires that the elder of the
house, you know, whoever's considered now the head of the household, obviously
these are a lot of presumably could be a lot of adult
people, you know, but nevertheless, you know, people tend to play the
roles they played growing up. So, you know, you often have the
oldest sibling or anyway you have somebody that's... I always seen exactly
how you identify who the גדול הבית gadol habayis is, it's an
interesting question, but assuming you could identify that person who is sort
of seen as the one in charge, you know, if that person
is present that defines it that the whole house, the whole family
is sitting שבעה shiva in this house and therefore this person even
though he wasn't physically there, maybe even if he didn't know about
it, is considered to be part of them. But if he wasn't
around, you know, he was off in Cleveland that's where he's sitting
שבעה shiva and everybody else lives in New York and they're sitting
over here and this person comes and from New Jersey and comes
to join them in New York and he found out a day
late, it's not like the whole family is observing together because one
of them is observing in... because the גדול הבית gadol habayis who
was a key part of defining the entity of the family is
not part... is not present. And therefore everybody observes, you know, counts
on their own individual account.
The גמרא Gemara is not talking about better, it's talking about just
the reality. איבעיא להו, Iba'yu lehu, no, there's no idea of like
preferring one or the other. איבעיא להו הלך גדול הבית לבית הקברות
מהו? Iba'yu lehu halach gadol habayis leveit hakevarot mahu? Now let's say
the גדול הבית gadol habayis followed the מת meis to the cemetery
and everybody else now turned around and began their שבעה shiva right
away because we're going to find out that if you don't follow
the מת meis to the cemetery you begin the שבעה shiva when
you turn your back, basically when you depart from the מת meis
and you know start returning back to where you're going to your
hometown. So that... or you know and you... so you give leave
of the מת. meis. So therefore the rest of the family began
on Monday. The גדול הבית gadol habayis accompanied the מת meis to
the cemetery, was only buried on Wednesday. He began on Wednesday. What
there is the story? Now it's a little bit of a question.
Is the question whether, you know, what's the story in terms of
the people that are... ...left behind, when did they begin if the
גדול הבית gadol habayis begins later? That's one type of a question
you could ask. Maybe the גדול הבית gadol habayis defines for everybody
else, okay, which is different than coming from a far way place
and rejoining. Maybe the question is somebody came from a far away
place and rejoined and or joined the family and the גדול הבית
gadol habayis wasn't there, but the reason he wasn't there was because
he was finishing up the process of the burial. So it's not
like he's distinct from their שבעה. shiva. They're all together. He's just
actually seeing the מת meis to the burial. He'll be returning and
therefore maybe it's still considered like you have the whole family unit
together even when the גדול הבית gadol habayis isn't present in that
case. So it's not exactly clear what the case is that the
גמרא Gemara is asking. Let's see what the answer is. A תא
שמע, ta shema, come here, דאמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי
יוחנן, da'amar Rabi Chiya bar Abba amar Rabi Yochanan, אפילו הלך גדול
הבית לבית הקברות מוני עמהן. afillu halach gadol habayis le-beis hakevaros monei
immahen. So even if he went to the בית הקברות, beis hakevaros,
he counts with them, which again, based on context, the simplest understanding
of this means that the person who is coming from New Jersey
and joined the people in New York, even though the גדול הבית
gadol habayis isn't there because the גדול הבית gadol habayis was accompanying
the מת meis to be buried in Israel, it's still not considered
like the lack of the full sense of the family as a
unit all sitting שבעה shiva because he's there because he's finishing up
the burial and he might even be returning later, although that's not
clear either.
What, the שאלה shayla is on the גדול הבית? gadol habayis? What?
The שאלה shayla is on the גדול הבית? gadol habayis?
No, I'm not reading it that way. That is another way to
read it. That's what תוספות Tosafot is reading it. No, the simple
context I think of the question is that ראובן Reuven is coming
from a nearby town and joining, well, not ראובן. Reuven. שמעון Shimon
is coming from a nearby town and joining לוי Levi ויהודה Yehuda
ויששכר Yissochar וזבולון, Zevulun, and ראובן Reuven isn't there because he's accompanying
the גדול... he's accompanying the מת. meis Right? So how much is
שמעון Shimon when he joins the other brothers, will he join in
with their counting? We just got told that if a גדול הבית
gadol habayis isn't there, it's not considered a family unit to the
same degree and he doesn't join their counting, but the reason the
גדול הבית gadol habayis is absent is because he's off burying the
dead body. אוי. oye. So that's the other read what דב Dov
suggested, which is the question about forget a person coming from another
place. What's the relationship of the גדול הבית gadol habayis and the
people left behind? And that is the other reading. There's two major
readings of that סוגיא. sugya. Okay, yes.
Why would you even imagine that the שבעה shiva begins before the
burial?
Yeah, well we're about to find that out. Okay. So that is
being taken for granted and we're about to find that out.
So let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
מוני עמהן, moni immahen, counts with those that are the person is
joining up with. והתניא, ve-hatanya, we teach in a ברייתא, Baraisa, מונה
לעצמו, monei le'atzmo, that the... now again this would be a case
of presumably the same type of a context of the גדול הבית
gadol habayis is away and a person is coming and joined, does
he count with them, does he count לעצמו? le'atzmo? לא קשיא, lo
kashya, הא דאתא בגו תלתא הא דלא אתא בגו תלתא. ha de'asa
be-go telassa ha de'lo asa be-go telassa. Is he coming within the
first three days or not coming within the first three days? Okay.
Now again, what again complicated what that means. It could mean whether
if this person joining the brothers is counts with them or not
if the גדול הבית gadol habayis isn't around because he's off with
the, you know, at the בית הקברות. beis hakevaros. So maybe it
depends whether the גדול הבית gadol habayis will be returning within the
first three days or not, right? To the degree to which you
can consider it now that everybody is together and the family is
together. He wouldn't necessarily know about that. That is if we're reading
it that the problem is the absence of the... well, but you'll
find out eventually. The problem is the absence of the גדול הבית
gadol habayis in order to allow everybody that remains to be considered
to be still one unit. That might depend on the גדול הבית
gadol habayis returning or not. Okay. Now, the גמרא Gemara says, כי
הא דאמר להו רב לבני
הסטטפוני, ki ha de'amar lehu Rav li-venai hastatpuni, like רב Rav said
to these people, דאתו בגו תלתא לימנו
בהדייכו, de-asu be-go telassa lemanei bahadaichu, whoever comes within the first three
days he should count with you. דלא אתו בגו תלתא לימנו לעצמייהו,
de-lo asu be-go telassa lemanei le-atpai, if you don't come within the
first three days, count for themselves. Now that sounds like forgetting about
the גדול הבית, gadol habayis, it's just going back to the earlier
point. Are you joining the rest of the family during the first
three days or not? If you're joining the rest of the family
during the first three days you count with them, if you're joining
after the first three days, you don't count with them. אמר להו
רבא לבני
מחוזא, amar lehu Rava li-venai Mechuza, now רבא Rava said to the
people of מחוזא, Mechuza, אתון דלא אזליתו בתר
ערסא, atun de-lo azlitu basar arsa, here you go, this is the
missing piece of the equation, you that do not follow after the
bier, so מכמה דהדרתו אפיכו מבאבא
דאבולא, mikama de-hadrisu apaichu mi-baba de-avula, when you turn your face from
the gate of the city, like when you get back into your
cars and are driving away from the airport, then you put the
מת meis on the plane to Israel, אתחילו מנו, atchilu manu, that's
when you should begin to count. And that actually is the הלכה,
halacha, right? So somebody is being put on a plane to Israel
to be buried, everybody who is left behind starts the שבעה shiva
right away. And that has to do with, you know, it's interesting,
on the one hand, the מת meis isn't buried. You know, we
talked before about the whole idea of שמועה רחוקה shmua rechoka and
being the problem that it's not just the subjective experience, it's relating
to the actual death and if the, you know, the deceased, and
if that's at a distance, it's not the same context of שבעה.
shiva. Here... Here it's a little bit here it's a little the
reverse. The person subjectively is begin is transitioning to the next state.
They're done with their אנינות aninus status. They're now, you know, they're
no longer the מת meis is in the process of being buried
and they have no connection to it. They've given their leave of
it. So the person psychologically, subjectively is moving on to the next
state, but the מת meis isn't buried yet. You're starting your, you
know, starting your שבעה shiva even before the the body is buried.
And that is a fascinating part of this הלכה. halacha. One thing
to think about that might help in understanding this is according to
some ראשונים, rishonim, a person really should be starting אבילות aveilus right
away. It's just that as soon as the person has died, it's
just that the אנינות aninus and the demands of אנינות aninus and
the psychological state of אנינות aninus overrides and takes precedence. And therefore
as soon as that no longer is present, the status of אבילות
aveilus kicks in. So that's the question: conceptually does אבילות aveilus need
for the מת meis? to be buried or does the אבילות aveilus
fundamentally need for the person not to be עסוק asuk with the
burial of the מת? meis Right? Interesting, you know, interesting questions here
that go on. But it's not always it's not it's not that
easy obviously. Somebody could be in Japan and not at all be
involved in the burial, but as long as the מת meis, isn't
in the process yet of about to be buried, that person would
not be starting, you know, their אבילות. aveilus. Interesting questions also about
their whole אנינות aninus status. You know, anyway, there's a lot of
fascinating questions here. But the key is number one is that אבילות
aveilus begins either at the time of burial or when the people
being taken to be buried and those that remain are turn back,
turn around and are heading home. That's point number one. And point
number two, this concept of the family sitting שבעה shiva and joining
in with the family. Joining in the first three days which are
the עיקר ikkar or on day seven, even up to day seven,
and the presence of the גדול הבית gadol habayis to help constitute
that as a family unit. And I think people probably who know
their own family dynamics it's not always that way but I think
we can to some degree relate to that reality that often occurs
that if there's a sort of central figure that helps sort of
bring it together that everybody is somehow coherent. And then the question
is what if the גדול הבית gadol habayis isn't there but he
isn't there for various reasons that's related will the family unit still
be seen as a coherent unit. Yes.
So רש״י Rashi says מבעבורה דאבולא משער החיצון. mibavuda deabula mishar hachitzon.
Is that a ירושלמי Yerushalmi phrase?
No, אבולא abula means the city. He just means that you're turning
back because you give your leave from the outer gate of the
city. Got it.
אבולא abula means city in Aramaic? Yeah. Or maybe it means an
אבל? ovel? But I don't think so.
I don't think so. Okay, I think it just means שער העיר.
shaar ha'ir. Okay. רבי שמעון אומר Rabbi Shimon Omer אפילו ב... afilu
ba... now we're going to finish this analysis that even joining in
on day seven according to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and that's the
ongoing discussion we've had. רבי שמעון אומר אפילו ביום השביעי ממקום קרוב
מוני עמהם. Rabbi Shimon Omer afilu b'yom hashevii mimakom karov moni imahem.
אמר רבי חייא בר גמדא אמר רבי יוסי בן שאול אמר רבי
Amar Rabbi Chiya bar Gamda amar Rabbi Yose ben Shaul amar Rebbe
והוא שבא ומצא מנחמים אצלו. vehu sheba umatzah menachamim etzlo. How do
you, how does somebody join the people during the day seven and
they're still sitting שבעה? shiva? Whatever happened to מקצת היום ככולו? miktzas
hayom kekulo? You join on day seven, they're already done. So it's
only if the person is still sitting, basically there're still מנחמים menachamim
there and they're still paying a final שבעה shiva call and therefore
still in the practice of שבעה, shiva, then you could the person
could be considered to be joining the family as they're sitting שבעה.
shiva. Okay, because the מנחמים menachamim are still there.
בעי רבי ענן Boei Rabbi Anan to רב ענן. Rav Anan. רב
ענן Rav Anan asked נינערו לעמוד ולא עמדו מהו. ninnaru laamod velo
amadu mahu. Let's say people are stirring themselves up and getting ready
to to leave the מנחמים, menachamim, but they haven't left yet and
then this person joins, came the family member came from an out
from a distant city just as people are in the process of
getting up from the שבעה. shiva. What's the story? And it says
תיקו. teiku. So that's left unanswered. I think everybody knows that phenomenon
when people start fidgeting it's clear they're trying to figure out how
they can get ready to go now. Anyway so if you're in
that state, is that still considered to be in the שבעה shiva
so when somebody joins he could become part of the family.
That's been unanswered too?
There you go. Exactly.
Okay, now the גמרא Gemara says like this: גמירי חבריה דרבי אבא
בר חייא מרבי אבא. gemiri chavrei d'Rabbi Abba bar Chiya m'Rabbi Abba.
So the the colleagues of רבי אבא בר חייא Rabbi Abba bar
Chiya learned from רבי אבא. Rabbi Abba. ומנו umannu and who are
the colleagues who are the colleague? רבי זירא. Rabbi Zeira. Okay. ואמרי
לה veamri lei and some say the reverse. חבריה דרבי זירא מרבי
זירא. chavrei d'Rabbi Zeira m'Rabbi Zeira. רבי זירא's Rabbi Zeira colleague learned
from רבי זירא. Rabbi Zeira. ומנו umannu and who was רבי זירא's
Rabbi Zeira colleague? רבי אבא בריה דרבי חייא בר אבא. Rabbi Abba
brei d'Rabbi Chiya bar Abba. רבי אבא Rabbi Abba the son of
חייא בר אבא. Chiya bar Abba. So one of them learned from
the other the following teaching. אמר רבי יוחנן Amar Rabbi Yochanan says
in the name of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan הלכה כרבי שמעון בן
גמליאל בטריפות. halacha k'Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel bitreifos. We rule like רבי
שמעון בן גמליאל Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel when it come in a
matter of טריפות. treifos. והלכה כרבי שמעון באבל. vehalacha k'Rabbi Shimon beavel.
And we rule like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon באבל. beavel. Very bizarre
putting these together. One's רבי שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel,
the other is רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. Anyway we rule by these
two דעת יחיד. das yachid. כרבי שמעון באבל הא דאמרן. k'Rabbi Shimon
beavel had amaran. Like רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon באבל beavel like we talked that even coming on
day seven. Again following the principle that הלכה כדברי המיקל, halacha k'divrei
hameikel, so even joining on day seven would be considered sharing in
their observance. כרבי שמעון בן גמליאל דתנן. k'Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel ditnan.
What's the פסק psak of רבי שמעון בן גמליאל? Rabbi Shimon ben
Gamliel? What he taught in the משנה? Mishna?
בני מעיים שניקבו, Bnei me'ayim shenikvu, if you have some of the
inner organs that got a hole in them to the טריפות treifus
issue. לחה סתמתה, lecha sotamtah, and the pus, some of the liquid,
the juices, fills up the hole and seals it. כשרה דברי רבן
גמליאל, Kasher divrei Rabban Gamliel, that is כשרה kasher and therefore it
is not considered a טריפה treifa because the hole is being internally
sealed. מאי לחה, Mai lecha, what is לחה? lecha? אמר רב כהנא,
Amar Rav Kahana, שיכא דמעייא, shika d'mei'aya, the sort of juices or
whatever of the viscous stuff of the organ, דנפיק אגב דוחקא, de'nafik
agav duchka, which comes out when you push it, when you press
against the
skin, it is exuded from the flesh. Okay, fine. We are not
going to get into that. אמר מר. Amar mar. Okay. אמר מנדהו.
Amar mandehu. Now somebody says, some anonymous person said, you have got
to love that, מנדהו, mandehu, מיהו שהוא, mihushehu, someone said, okay. אזכי
דאסיק ואגמר שמעתא מפומא דמאריה, Izki de'asik v'agmar shemaita mipumah demarei, I
should only merit and go ahead and learn this teaching from the
mouth of its master, meaning I want to hear this from the
horse's mouth, as a way of saying that. I want to make
sure I really got this teaching correct. Okay, so let's take a
look. כי סליק, Ki salik, when he went up to ארץ ישראל,
Eretz Yisrael, אשכחיה לרבי אבא בריה דרבי חייא בר אבא. askchei l'Rabbi
Abba brei d'Rabbi Chiya bar Abba. He found רבי אבא, Rabbi Abba,
who according to one version of the story was the author of
this statement. רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom says or רבי זירא, Rabbi Zeira,
according to the other version of the story. Anyway, he found the
author of this statement. אמר ליה, Amar lei, אמר מר הלכה כרבן
גמליאל בטריפות? amar mar lacha k'Rabban Gamliel bitreifus? Did you really say
we rule like רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel by טריפות? treifus? Obviously that
was bothering him, he was astounded that we could rule that way.
אמר ליה, Amar lei, אנא אין הלכה אמרי. ana ein halacha amri.
I said the הלכה halacha is not like רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel
by טריפות, treifus, so it is a good thing you came to
check what I really said because they missed the little word not.
Okay, so אין הלכה אמרי. ein halacha amri. How about כרבי שמעון
באבל מאי, k'Rabbi Shimon ba'avel mai, what about רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
by אבל, avel, joining on day seven as opposed to joining on
day three? So אמר ליה, Amar lei, he said to him, פלוגתא,
pelugta, that is a matter of debate. דאתמר, De'itmar, it was taught,
רב חסדא אמר הלכה, Rav Chisda amar halacha, רב חסדא Rav Chisda
says we rule like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon even arriving on day
seven. וכן אמר רבי יוחנן הלכה, V'chen amar Rabbi Yochanan halacha, and
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says we rule like him even arriving on
day seven. רב נחמן אמר אין הלכה, Rav Nachman amar ein halacha,
we do not rule like him. So there that remains a matter
of debate. Concludes the anonymous voice of the גמרא, Gemara, דאין הלכה
כרבן גמליאל בטריפות. de'ein halacha k'Rabban Gamliel bitreifus. We do not rule
like רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel by טריפות, treifus, that is a big
leniency. But והלכה כרבי שמעון באבל, v'halacha k'Rabbi Shimon ba'avel, we do
rule like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon by אבל avel even coming on
day seven. And he guesses why? דאמר שמואל הלכה כדברי המיקל באבל,
D'amar Shmuel halacha k'divrei hameikil ba'avel, because שמואל Shmuel says we rule
like the lenient position by אבל, avel, a recurring theme of this
מסכת. Masechet. Okay, yes.
Yes, we had these two little phrases, would you remind us please,
what is the import of דאתמר itmar and of אמר מר? amar
mar?
Yeah, דאתמר itmar means, no, not דאתמר itmar and אמר מר, amar
mar, דאתמר itmar and גופא gufa and אמר מר. amar mar. גופא
gufa is like, let's take, we quoted an excerpt from something, now
let's look at the entire passage. אמר מר Amar mar means we
quoted a line and now let's like go into it in greater
depth. So that is the basic difference of those two. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay, where were we? הכל המתים כולן מדרחימי תפוץ הרי זה משובח.
Ha'kol hameisin kulan medachmeitatzu harei zeh meshubach. By all other, by all
normal cases of people who have passed away, the person, the mourner,
who literally
rinses out his bed, cleans out the bed quicker,
cleaning out the bed is praised, which what it means is it
is an interesting euphemism, it means speedy burial. The person, the bed
is the deathbed, and the person who ensures that the person is
buried quicker, that is a positive thing.
You do not want a מת, meis hold on, you do not
want a מת sitting around, especially before refrigeration and so on. אביו
ואמו הרי זה מגונה. Aviv v'imo harei zeh meguneh. But somebody who
does it who overly quickly moves on to the burial by a
mother and a father, that is considered to be non-praiseworthy,
blameworthy. Now why? So I do not think it is what Michael
said to get more people present, I think anyway everybody was mostly
local and people in the town and so on. I think it
is the question about how ready you are to take your leave,
how ready you are to transition to the next stage. And therefore
there should be that sense of that final holding on and that
sort of, it is funny, you talk about the seven stages about
denial and then whatever, etc. So I think what the גמרא Gemara
is saying is a certain respect of אביו ואמו Aviv v'imo needs
a little bit of denial, a little sense of refusal, not ready
to move on to the next stage. And I am not saying
that is necessarily psychologically healthy, but we can have the psychiatrist tell
us, psychologist tell us what the story is with that. So maybe
denial is putting it too far, but at least a hesitation of
not yet ready to move on to the burial. And therefore it
says that that is הרי זה משובח. harei zeh meshubach. No, my
question was what takes more כבוד? kavod? I understand, so that is
a different discussion, but that is what we are talking about all
the. and that's all things being equal. ערב שבת erev Shabbat or
ערב יום טוב, erev Yom Tov, if it's right before שבת Shabbos
or right before יום טוב, Yom Tov, and if you don't take
care of it now, it's going to have to wait to be
buried at least a day or more, I mean even יום טוב
Yontif second day they would bury, so at least a day, הרי
זה משובח, harei zeh meshubach, then it is praiseworthy to make sure
that the burial occurs during the, you know, before שבת Shabbos and
יום טוב Yontif hit.
Okay, שאינו עושה אלא לכבוד אביו ואמו, she'eino oseh ela likhvod aviv
ve'imo, in that case it's clear that it's being done for honoring
the father and mother in order to ensure that the body doesn't
wait around an extra day. Okay, כל המתים כולן רצה למעט עסקו
רצה אינו ממעט, kol hamesin kulan ratza lema'et isko ratza eino mima'et,
by all other cases of death, the אבל avel who wants
to limit his business dealings or not. Fascinating because you're not supposed
to be doing מלאכה. melakha. So is there a difference between מלאכה
melakha and עסקין? asakin? Are עסקין asakin business dealings? Or עסקין asakin
we have a lot of עסקין asakin that are not business dealings,
right? You know, we can have a lot of things that occupy
us that are not business dealings, but anyway, it could be רבנו
גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom here says, I believe says business dealings, כגון סחורה.
kegon sekhora. Okay, that's not just מקח וממכר, mekach umimkar, that's not
just going to the store and buying a quart of milk. You
know, but so what does it mean? Aren't you supposed to? So
is there basically a difference between sort of commerce as opposed to
מלאכה, melakha, which is more like labor, you know, sort of, you
know, and that's the distinction that's being made? A number of ראשונים
rishonim say, no, no, no, we mean this is included in the
איסור מלאכה, issur melakha, but what we mean is even when there
are allowances for מלאכה, melakha, like דבר האבד davar ha'aved and other
types of allowances, בצנעה בתוך ביתו betzina betokh beito after the first
three days, etc. If a person wants to be מחמיר, mahmir, fine.
You don't want to be מחמיר mahmir with those allowances, also fine.
על אביו ועל אמו ממעט. al aviv ve'al imo mima'et. But by
father and mother a person should look to make sure even when
there are allowances to limit any other any of these types of
dealings. So again, fascinating question just in terms of what is this
telling us about the איסור מלאכה? issur melakha? Are we fundamentally making
two categories, you know, sort of commerce versus מלאכה? melakha? Are we
saying that this is not even talking about business, it's talking about
just general types of עסקין, asakin, general types of, you know, involvements
that a person is doing, other types of activities? Or is it
not telling us any of that and it's telling us that we're
talking about cases where we would otherwise allow it, like דבר האבד
davar ha'aved and so on? So there's a lot of interesting discussion
around this.
I think it's already from Ezra Nehemiah that business transactions seem to
be its own category לגבי שבת. legabei Shabbat.
By שבת, Shabbat, correct. But that, you know, but for אבלות avelut
there's the question. Now, of course some people will argue that by
Ezra Nehemiah that actually shows that business was more central part of
שבת Shabbat than the sort of, you know, than it is in
the understanding of חזל, Chazal, you know, the later framing about the
ל"ט מלאכות lamed tes melakhot and business dealings gets to be just
some type of דרבנן, derabbanan, right? So there is interest... anyway, but
there's interesting questions about that.
Okay, כל המתים כולן, kol hamesin kulan, so that was again, so
a lot of different things here, right? One is just מנהגי אבלות
minhagei avelut and area to be a little bit פרומער frummer on
during,
you know, in some practices. There was the issue about the speed
of burial, and now we get to other types of practices that
we haven't even heard too much about. One is קריעה kriya and
related things, although we have mentioned doing קריעה מעומד. kriya me'umad. Let's
take a look. כל המתים כולן רצה חולץ רצה אינו חולץ. kol
hamesin kulan ratza choletz ratza eino choletz.
By all other relatives, if a person wants, they can uncover their
shoulder and if they want they don't uncover their shoulder. So that
was seen as a practice of אבלות, avelut, to basically take one's
garment, you know, expose the shoulder. על אביו ועל אמו חולץ. al
aviv ve'al imo choletz. By father and mother a person in addition
to doing קריעה kriya is also supposed to do the exposing of
the shoulder. ומעשה בגדול הדור אחד כמת אביו. uma'aseh begadol hador echad
kemes aviv. There was a story about one great leader of the
generation, you see the concept of a גדול הדור gadol hador is
already in the גמרא, Gemara, one great leader of the generation whose
father died, וביקש לחלוץ, uvikesh lachlot,
and he wanted to do חליצה, chalitza, to expose his shoulder. וביקש
גדול הדור אחר שעמו לחלוץ, uvikesh gadol hador acher she'imo lachlot, and
another great of the generation, so there's not just one גדול הדור,
gadol hador, who was with him, wanted to say, oh if you're
going to do that, then out of deference and respect to you
and to your אבלות, avelut, he also was going to do חליצה,
chalitza, you know, expose his shoulder. And again there is a question,
it's one thing, you know, your private individual, you want to express
this grief, but you're also a public individual. גדול הדור gadol hador
here also presumably has not is not just like it's used nowadays,
like oh a big תורה Torah scholar, but it's somebody also that
has a sort of political status within the... you know, political-religious status
within the society. So is that appropriate? So he felt, look, for
the guy the one who was the אבל avel felt for himself
to be doing that and to sort of be giving this private
this personal expression of grief, even though he was a גדול הדור
gadol hador was appropriate. But if it's going to lead to this
other person doing it, who's not an אבל, avel, then that's going
to be inappropriate for this person and for his status in society
to be acting in this like, you know, less than
honorable way that's not about sort of... know that that's somewhat inappropriate
for his status.
So, therefore, what did he do? ונמנע ולא חלץ, venimna velo chalatz,
so the אבל avel chose not to do חליצה chalitza so the
other one wouldn't do it together with him. Okay, now who are
these people? אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, גדול הדור, gadol hador, the great
of the generation, was רבי. Rebbi. גדול הדור שעמו, Gadol hador she'imo,
and his colleague who was with him, was רבי יעקב בר אחא.
Rabbi Yaakov bar Acha. רבי יעקב בר אחא, Rabbi Yaakov bar Acha,
which is fascinating, if I asked you to name who do you
think would be a גדול הדור gadol hador in the time of
רבי, Rebbi, you probably wouldn't even know that רבי יעקב בר אחא
Rabbi Yaakov bar Acha lived in the time of רבי. Rebbi. So,
okay, so that's that.
ואביו ואמו? Ve'aviv ve'imo?
ואיכא דאמרי, Ve'ika de'amri, yeah, this is presumably אביו ואמו. aviv ve'imo.
ואיכא דאמרי, Ve'ika de'amri, others say, גדול הדור, gadol hador, because the
גמרא Gemara just says you should, it's not exactly clear at which
stage here,
these becomes absolute הלכה halachic demands. We don't do חליצה chalitza nowadays.
Okay. ואיכא דאמרי, Ve'ika de'amri, others say,
גדול הדור רבי יעקב בר אחא, gadol hador Rabbi Yaakov bar Acha,
no, the first one who was the אבל avel was יעקב בר
אחא. Yaakov bar Acha. גדול הדור שעמו, Gadol hador she'imo, the one
with him, was רבי. Rebbi. So it was still like the previous
story, they were both involved, the question was who was who. Okay.
בשלמא, Bishlama, says
the גמרא, Gemara, it's good, למאן דאמר גדול הדור שעמו רבי, leman
de'amar gadol hador she'imo Rebbi, היינו דנמנע ולא חלץ. hainu denimna velo
chalatz. You understand why רבי Rebbi didn't do it- why רבי אחא
Rabbi Acha didn't do it, so רבי Rebbi wouldn't be forced to
do it. And obviously רבי Rebbi was the גדול הדור gadol hador
and he didn't want רבי Rebbi to be demonstrating this, especially if
רבי Rebbi himself wasn't the אבל. avel. אלא, Ella, but according to
the first version, למאן דאמר רבי יעקב בר אחא, leman de'amar Rabbi
Yaakov bar Acha, רבי יעקב בר אחא- Rabbi Yaakov bar Acha I'm
sorry, the second version- רבי יעקב- Rabbi Yaakov no, the first version-
רבי יעקב בר אחא Rabbi Yaakov bar Acha was the colleague, and
רבי Rebbi was the one in שבעה, shiva, אמאי נמנע ולא חלץ?
amai nimna velo chalatz? Why did רבי Rebbi not do it so
רבי יעקב בר אחא Rabbi Yaakov bar Acha wouldn't join him? רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל נשיא הוה. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel nasi hava. רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, who is- who's רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל? Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel?
רבי's Rebbi father. So we assume here because the context was אביו
ואמו, aviv ve'imo, doing חליצה chalitza for אביו ואמו, aviv ve'imo, somehow
we assume father rather than mother, I don't know why. So if
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, רבי's Rebbi father had
died, and that's why רבי Rebbi was doing חליצה, chalitza, so רבי
יעקב בר אחא Rabbi Yaakov bar Acha has to do חליצה chalitza
not just to respect רבי, Rebbi, but because the נשיא הדור nasi
hador has died. So נשיא היה, nasi haya, ובכולי עלמא מיחייב למיחלץ.
uvechulei alma michayav lemichlatz. Everybody would have to do חליצה. chalitza. So
he's not just doing it out of respect for רבי. Rebbi. קשיא.
Kashya. Okay, that's a good question. So now we have introduced an
interesting idea, which is number one, doing שבעה shiva for the גדול
הדור, gadol hador, for a נשיא. nasi. And number two- well, not
שבעה, shiva, let's not jump ahead, doing קריעה kriah and maybe also
חליצה, chalitza, and putting it in the same category as אביו ואמו.
aviv ve'imo. Not just that you would do קריעה kriah for a
נשיא, nasi, you would do חליצה chalitza which right now is limited
to the case of אביו ואמו. aviv ve'imo. Yes.
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel was named as one
of the עשרה הרוגי מלכות. Asara Harugei Malchut. Is this this רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel or the earlier one?
No, it would be this one. That would be the Hadrianic persecutions,
which is a generation before רבי. Rebbi.
So he would have- good point. I don't know, I guess he
would have had- sat שבעה shiva for him whether he was martyred
or died naturally. But yeah, interesting. Okay, yes.
Aside from the fact that מפרשים mefarshim say so, is there any
reason that we know that this חליצה chalitza is the כתף katef
and not shoes?
Well, we already know נעילת הסנדל neilat hasandal was completely a basic
staple of אבילות. aveilus. We never would have suggested that it- and
anyway, we never refer to it as חליצה, chalitza, we always refer
to it as נעילת הסנדל, neilat hasandal, and it's clear that it
applies to all אבלים. avelim. So חליצה chalitza clearly is something else.
I mean, you're thinking about the- about יבום, yibbum, וחלצה נעלו. vechaltsa
na'alo. ולחלוץ velachlotz just means to
remove. So the context is necessary. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says
okay. הכל מקימין כולן. Hakol mekimin kulan.
Now, it is true I sort of said to Michael a minute
ago and I probably shouldn't have said it, that how much is
this being framed as should or must?
In the early- in the first stage it's about ממעט בעסקו. mema'et
be'isko. It's a very non-quantifiable
position. If you want to tell me certain things are אסור assur
for אביו ואמו, aviv ve'imo, that you don't have certain היתרים heterim
or whatever, say אסור. assur. ממעט Mema'et is a discretionary type of
a thing. How much is
ממעט? mema'et? I mean, you have to be ממעט, mema'et, but it's
still not black and white. The other idea about- about
מזחח מטתו, mezachach mittato, quick burial. What's quick, what's slow, what's postponed?
But now we're talking- so you could have said some of those
are more guidelines than הלכה. halacha. But here we're talking about to
be חולץ, choleitz, which is an absolute demand. And now the rest
of these discussions about things that a person does for אביו ואמו
aviv ve'imo are understood as very black and white הלכות, halachos, not
like preferable guidelines type of a thing. So it is interesting, because
some of the earlier stuff was a little vaguer, but now we're
going to much more- we clearly don't do חליצה chalitza for
אביו ואמו, aviv ve'imo, but we're going to much more concrete types
of behaviors. So let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says
like this.
Okay. הכל מקימין כולן Hakol mekimin kulan מסתפר לאחר שלשים יום. mistaper
le'achar sheloshim yom. For all normal cases of relatives who die, a
person
can you need to get a haircut. Okay. But even if it's
within 30 days, you don't listen to them? Is that only...
Right, that does not compromise the 30 days. It's only after 30
days. Right, there's obviously an idea of שלושים shloshim that's not related
to that. Okay, so
now by the way, there's an interesting תוספות, Tosafot, if you look
at תוספות, Tosafot, תוספות Tosafot says, okay, תוספות Tosafot says, yeah we
do that. עד שיגערו בו חבריו נראה דרגל אינו מבטל דבר זה.
Ad she'yig'aru bo chaverav nireh de'regel eino mevatel davar zeh. Right? It's
not about the רגל regel because רגל regel relates to the time
period you're in. This has to do with the state of dishevelment
which is not a function of whether there was a רגל regel
or not. וגרסינן בירושלמי, Vegarsinan bi'Yerushalmi, רבי שמואל בר אבדימי דמנא תלתין
יומין קמי מועדא, Rabbi Shmuel bar Avdimi de'mana telatin yomin kammai mo'ada,
he counted 30 days before the יום טוב. Yom Tov. שאל לרבי
מנא, Sha'al le'Rabbi Mana, he asked Rabbi Mana. אמר ליה, Amar lei,
כל דבר שהוא תלוי בשבעה ושלושים הרגל מפסיק בהם, kol davar she'hu
talui be'shiva ve'shloshim ha'regel mafsik bahem, anything that's based on שבעה shiva
or שלושים, shloshim, it's a time period, רגל regel changes the time
period. ברם הכא, Beram hacha, but here, עד שישלח פרע ויגערו בו
חבריו, ad she'yishlach pera ve'yig'aru bo chaverav, until the hair grows wild
and the friends yell at you,
ויאמרו לו צא מעמנו, ve'yomeru lo tze mi'immanu, get out of, leave
us, you're not appropriate, like we don't want to be hanging around
you, you're looking too disheveled. Okay. And then תוספות Tosafot points out,
and I'll prove to you some things רגל regel doesn't interrupt because
there's an idea of אביו ואמו, aviv ve'immo, certain things that go
for 12 months. Well, there tends to be a lot of רגלים
regalim in 12 months, so clearly. So that's another way of saying
it, that things that are beyond שלושים, shloshim, רגל regel doesn't interrupt.
But conceptually he was saying a different point, this is not about
a period of time, this is about an appearance and therefore it's
not affected by the רגל. regel.
You still can't get your haircut on רגל regel meaning like you've
had your 30 days and then you
enter into the רגל. regel. Right, that would be... that might be.
Okay.
So it's also a soft criteria for a הלכה. halacha.
עד שיגערו בו חבריו?
Ad she'yig'aru bo chaverav? Yeah. It's true.
Not only is it soft, it's a very idiosyncratic definition.
What do you mean?
It doesn't say when the authority tells you, it says when your
social group tells you.
Yeah. Right.
That's a thing we are allowed to sort of have somebody...
Yeah, people sometimes do that, you know. Yeah, I didn't, I don't
know. Anyway, על כל המתים כולם, Al kol ha'metim kulam, you're not
supposed to ask but people who are in the know know to
go over to an אבל avel and say you know I think
it's time you get a haircut. על כל המתים כולם נכנס לבית
השמחה לאחר שלושים יום, Al kol ha'metim kulam nichnas le'veit ha'simcha le'achar
shloshim yom, for all other relatives a person can go into the
drinking hall, בית השמחה, beit ha'simcha, excuse me, into a joyous occasion
after 30 days. על אביו ועל אמו לאחר י"ב חודש, Al aviv
ve'al immo le'achar yud bet chodesh, for mother and father it's 12
months. And this is the biggest practice, you know, for parents which
is the idea of not sort of doing these activities, these joyous
you know social activities for a year. The question is exactly what
are the parameters. Right, does it involve eating and drinking? Does it
involve music? Exactly what are the parameters is a big, one of
the big questions by אבילות aveilut because it also lasts a very
long time.
It also makes a difference who it is. Like let's say it's
your kid.
Right, exactly. Is the fact that it's a שמחת מצוה simchat mitzvah
does that make it better or does it make it worse? Because
you could say well if it's a... like if it's a wedding,
that makes it even more of a שמחה. simcha. On the other
hand, it's a מצוה mitzvah that should be given an allowance. So
these are issues that are much debated in the ראשונים. Rishonim. The
גמרא Gemara is extremely terse about these. Okay. So let's take a
look.
על אביו ועל אמו לאחר י"ב חודש. Al aviv ve'al immo le'achar
yud bet chodesh. אמר רבה בר בר חנה: Amar Rabbah bar bar
Chana: ולשמחת מרעות, U'le'simchat mere'ut, and...
but... but... that's exactly unclear, what does he mean ולשמחת מרעות? u'le'simchat
mere'ut? So take a look at רבנו גרשום, Rabbeinu Gershom, the first
narrow line. סעודה שעושים רעים ואוהבים זה עם זה ולא הוי שמחה
כל כך, Se'udah she'osim re'im ve'ohavim zeh im zeh ve'lo havei simcha
kol kach, it's like a social gathering, it's not a major joyous
occasion, it's just a lot of friends getting together.
אבל סעודה דשמחה כגון נישואין לא. Aval se'udah de'simcha kegon nisuin lo.
So he says that... I'm sorry, but also the first line, what
is he qualifying, אמר רבה, Amar Rabbah, the last of the wide
lines
here, הא דתניא נכנס לבית המשתה לאחר שלושים יום לשמחת מרעות. ha
de'tanya nichnas le'veit ha'mishteh le'achar shloshim yom le'simchat mere'ut. Meaning he's saying
when we allow a normal אבל avel to do joyous gatherings after
30 days, it's not really joyous gatherings. He can do social gatherings,
he can do friendly gatherings, but he can't go to like a
real big party. Okay, now exactly what exactly is the line between
those? Again, is it maybe a בית השמחה beit ha'simcha like a
wedding? You know, does מצוה mitzvah make it better or make it
worse? That's the question. But anyway, according to this, we don't פסקן
pasken this way as I'm sure you know. Nobody ever heard that
when it's not a parent that there's observance that lasts for 12
months. But he actually is saying no, even not a parent to
do you know, we will allow a person to do social gatherings
but not to do real activities that are really like major joyous
activities. Okay, the גמרא Gemara is going to give a different version
in a minute. Let's take a look.
ולשמחת מרעות, U'le'simchat mere'ut, that... what is allowed after שלושים shloshim is
only שמחת מרעות, simchat mere'ut, only a joy of friends, not a
major like public joyous experience. מיתיבי, Meitivei, I'll ask you on this.
We have a ברייתא Braitah that says
ולשמחה ולמרעות שלושים יום. ul'simcha ul'merayeos shloshim yom. The prohibitions of שמחה
simcha and of social gatherings are thirty days, which means that after
thirty days, they're both allowed. So even a full שמחה. simcha. So
קשיא, kasha, that's difficult. אמימר מתני הכי, Ameimar masni hachi, Ameimar teaches
the following: אמר רב בר בר חנה ולשמחת מרעות מותר להכנס לאלתר,
Amar Rabba bar bar Chana ul'simchas merayeos mutar l'hikaneis l'alter, a much
more lenient teaching. Guess which way we're going to פסקן, pasken, okay?
When it's not a major joyous activity, it's just a social gathering,
that a person can do right away, presumably right away means after
שבעה, shiva, not that you have to wait thirty days. Not for
father or mother, okay? So major joyous, that's all thirty days, but
just a social gathering, that's okay even within the first thirty days,
okay, which is important, right, which then conceptually would mean that for
father and mother, if you sort of carry that logic, it would
mean for father and mother, the big שמחה simcha is אסור assur
for י"ב חודש. yud beis chodesh. If you carry that sort of
distinction over, the big שמחה simcha is אסור assur for י"ב חודש,
yud beis chodesh, but the שמחת מרעות simchas merayeos would be allowed
for י"ב חודש. yud beis chodesh. Okay, we tend to not distinguish
in practice either way, we tend to say for normally for שלושים
יום, shloshim yom, right,
you know, for normal אבל avel שלושים יום, shloshim yom, שמחה, simcha,
שמחת מרעות, simchas merayeos, whatever, they're sort of equally אסור. assur. And
after שלושים יום shloshim yom they're equally מותר, mutar, and for י"ב
חודש yud beis chodesh we say for אביו ואמו aviv v'imo whether
שמחה simcha or שמחת מרעות simchas merayeos is like equally אסור. assur.
That sort of tends to be the general thrust, because when you
hear people talk about י"ב חודש, yud beis chodesh, you hear them
talking about, oh what's the definition of שמחת מרעות? simchas merayeos? According
to what we just read, it should have been what's bigger than
שמחת מרעות. simchas merayeos. שמחת מרעות simchas merayeos should have been allowed,
you know? So anyway, the גמרא Gemara makes distinctions with this, but
we sort of tend to conflate the categories, okay? But right now
what we're saying is שמחת מרעות simchas merayeos is allowed for a
normal person right away, presumably even during שלושים. shloshim. It's only big
שמחה simcha that's the problem, and that would be a problem for
אביו ואמו aviv v'imo י"ב חודש. yud beis chodesh. גמרא Gemara says
והתניא ולשמחה שלושים ולמרעות שלושים. v'hatanya ul'simcha shloshim ul'merayeos shloshim. But one
minute, we taught that they're non-distinct, both שמחה simcha and מרעות merayeos
are thirty days, there's no more leniency to מרעות. merayeos. לא קשיא,
lo kashya, it's not difficult. הא באריסותא הא בפורענותא. ha b'arisusa ha
b'puranusa.
The question is whether it is the first sort of offering or
the paying back. They had a practice that basically, you know, everybody
would get together, I don't know, once a month, or I don't
know, somebody would decide to get his friends together and to throw
a party for all of his friends, and then there once that
initial party was thrown, then everybody else would have to reciprocate within
the course of the year. So that's a שמחת מרעות, simchas merayeos,
a bunch of friends getting together, it's friendly, it's joyous, it's not
a big wedding party with a band, okay, and there the גמרא
Gemara says there's a difference. If you have to initiate, you're not
supposed to do all שלושים יום. shloshim yom. If it's your turn
to pay back, then there's a sense of shirking your responsibilities, then
you're going to do it even during the שלושים יום. shloshim yom.
And now you understand, yeah, of course you're going to understand, now
you understand why we don't tend to distinguish, because what we're basically
saying is other than a special case of reciprocating, שמחה simcha and
מרעות merayeos are being treated the same. שמחה simcha and מרעות merayeos
are equally אסור assur all שלושים יום shloshim yom except for the
special case of reciprocating, and that's for a normal person, for a
normal sort of שבעה. shiva. And for אביו ואמו aviv v'imo we
would then say that it would be
presumably both אסור assur all י"ב חודש. yud beis chodesh. So that's
why you will hear people when they're asking questions about can I
go to this event, can I go to the movies, can I
do this, can I have people over Shabbos, is like, well what's
the definition of שמחת מרעות? simchas merayeos? Which is less than full
שמחה. simcha. שמחת מרעות simchas merayeos means even if it's a certain
type of a social context, it's not a full-blown שמחה, simcha, but
with a component of שמחה, simcha, you know, it's a problem. מרעות
merayeos isn't a problem, although it's interesting, the ברייתא Braitah said מרעות
merayeos by itself, but conceptually it gets to be understood more the
combination of the שמחת מרעות, simchas merayeos, social with a joyous element.
And exactly how to define that parameters is not so clear. We'll
see if I have a minute I'll read you some lines from
תוספות. Tosafos. Okay,
let's do a little bit more. הכל המיתים כולם קורע טפח. hacol
hameisim kulam koreia tefach. Now we move to קריעה. kria. By all
other relatives a person does a טפח tefach of the קריעה, kria,
like three, four inches. על אביו ועל אמו עד שיגלה לבו. al
aviv v'al imo ad sheyigaleh libo. Mother and father it has to
render garment so much that it exposes opposite the heart. Obviously that
has very symbolic significance, yes. אמר רבי אבהו מאי קרא, amar Rabbi
Abbahu mai kra, where do you see this? ויחזק דוד בבגדיו ויקרעם.
vayechezek David bivgadav vayikra'eim. David hold onto his garment and he rent
them. ואין אחיזה פחות מטפח, v'ein achiza pachas mit'fach, and so that
wasn't in the context of אביו ואמו, aviv v'imo, but to hold
on, the size of your hand is a טפח. tefach. So therefore,
and somehow we are understanding that he rent them opposite where his
hand was, the length of the טפח. tefach. I don't know. How
do they get that אחיזה achiza is a טפח? tefach? Because you're
אוחז ocheiz with your hand and your hand is a טפח. tefach.
Okay, how do we know that he rent opposite his hand, that
I don't know. הכל המיתים כולם ואפילו לבוש עשרה חלוקין אינו קורע
אלא עליון. hacol hameisim kulam v'afilu lavush asara chalukin eino koreia ela
elyon. By
all other relatives even if there's ten garments, it's only tearing the
first garment. על אביו ועל אמו קורע את כולם. al aviv v'al
imo koreia es kulam. קורע את כולן koreh et kulan by mother
and father tear all the way through all of the garments, to
expose one's, again, to expose one's heart, part of the same type
of an idea.
ואף האפיקרסוטו אינה מעכבת. ve'af ha'afikarsuto eina me'akevet. His אפיקרסוט afikarsut does
not withhold, does not hold back. What does that mean? So רבינו
גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom says it means some type of a turban, which
is like bizarre, since when were we talking, did we think you
would do a turban? We didn't think you would do your socks
or your pants. So others say basically means an undershirt, that even
by father and mother, עד שיגלה לבו ad sheyigaleh libo doesn't mean
fully, literally something that's not really considered a garment, something that's just
there to absorb sweat like an undergarment would not have to be
rent, which is funny because the frame is עד שיגלה לבו. ad
sheyigaleh libo. No, okay. אחד האיש ואחד האשה,
echad
ha'ish
ve'echad ha'isha,
no difference between man or woman is the first statement. ורבי שמעון
בן אלעזר אומר, ve'Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar omer, האשה קורעת את התחתון,
ha'isha kora'at et hatachton, no, in case of a parent where there
is an issue of totally tearing all the way down, the woman
would tear the undergarment, the lower garment, not the undergarment, the one
that's underneath, ומחזירתו לאחוריה, umachzirato leachoreiha,
and then reverse it so that now the tear is on her
back, not on her front, and then וחוזרת וקורעת את העליון vechozeret
vekora'at et ha'elyon and then rends
the upper garment so that even though she's rent both the outer
and the inner garment, but her chest is not exposed. על כל
המתים כולן רוצה מבדיל כמי שפת שלא רוצה אינו מבדיל, al kol
hametim kulan rotze mavdil kimei sfat shelo rotze eino mavdil, by all
other מתים, metim, if somebody wants they will rend opposite the hem,
presumably the hem around the neck although there's a question of exactly
how to read this. על אביו ועל אמו מבדיל, al aviv ve'al
imo mavdil, by mother and father one has to rend you know
even starting from the hem of the garment and rend down all
the way make it into a fully like two halves. אמר רבי
יהודה, amar Rabbi Yehuda, כל קריעה שאינה מבדיל כמי שפת אינה אלא
קריאה של תפלות. kol kriah she'eina mavdil kimei sfat eina ela kriah
shel tiflut.
He basically rejects the distinction of אביו ואמו aviv ve'imo and others
and says that any rending that does not actually rend opposite the
hem is nonsense. אמר רבי אבא, amar Rabbi Abba, מאי טעמא דרבי
יהודה? mai ta'ama deRabbi Yehuda? What's his reasoning? דכתיב, dechativ, the verse
says ויחזק בבגדיו ויקרעם לשנים
קרעים, vayechezek bivgadav vayikra'em lishnayim kera'im, he held onto his garments and
he rent them into two you know tears. ממשמע שנאמר ויקרעם, mimashma
shene'emar vayikra'em, איני
יודע שהן שנים? eini yode'a shehen shnayim?
Of course they're two. אלא שנראין כקרועים לשנים. ela shene'erin kikeru'im lishnayim.
So why does it mean to two?
It has to look like two halves. So if it's a rent
in the middle of the garment it doesn't look like two halves.
If it's a rending that begins from the you know from the
what do you call it from the hem, it really breaks the
garment into two halves. Okay. על כל המתים כולן שולל אחר שבעה
ומאחה אחר שלשים. al kol hametim kulan sholel achar shiva um'acheh achar
shloshim.
By all other relatives a person can like somewhat you know pin
them together essentially after seven days, fix the hem, and after thirty
days can actually like do a serious stitching of it together, actual
like a weaving of it together. על אביו ועל אמו שולל אחר
שלשים, al aviv ve'al imo sholel achar shloshim, by mother and father
a person would wait till after שלשים shloshim to even do a
loose type of binding, ואינו מאחה לעולם, ve'eino m'acheh l'olam, can never
fully sew it together. So all of these distinctions and again the
important point to remember is that the פוסקים, poskim, the גמרא Gemara
says it in other cases כבוד אביו ואמו, kvod aviv ve'imo, and
that tends to be the point repeated by the פוסקים. poskim. It's
not to say that necessarily this is a you know again every
case is different but you
know often if we think about who a person might be sitting
שבעה shiva for, a child חס ושלום chas veshalom or a spouse
can often be much more devastating to a person than mother and
father, depends on the case obviously. So the פוסקים poskim really make
a point that this is part of the קיום kiyum of כיבוד
אב ואם, kibbud av va'em, it's not necessarily a means to be
expressing that this is more tragic than other deaths, but it's part
of the aspect of קיום kiyum of כיבוד אב ואם kibbud av
va'em which is done even after they've passed away.
You also can't quantify the intensity of the emotional response.
Right, but what some people read this is that we are quantifying
that there's more emotional response by אביו ואמו. aviv ve'imo. Okay, you
can't fully quantify but it seems to say אביו ואמו aviv ve'imo
is more. Right, exactly.
Exactly. Oh I see, you wouldn't even want to try to create
a hierarchy of emotional response is what you're saying, right? Okay, I
see. Yes. Okay. והאשה שוללת לאלתר, veha'isha sholelet le'altar,
but a woman could again not do a full sewing but you
know sort of immediately repin it מפני כבודה, mipnei kevoda, again because
of her honor
and that's so similar to some of the issues before. כי אתא
רבין אמר רבי יוחנן, ki ata Ravin amar Rabbi Yochanan, when רבין
Ravin came from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael said in the name of
רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, על כל המתים רוצה קורע ביד רוצה קורע
בכלי, al kol hametim rotze koreh beyad rotze koreh bichli, by all
relatives a person can either do it with his hands or with
a like scissors to get it started. על אביו ועל אמו ביד,
al aviv ve'al imo beyad, mother and father it has to be
by the hand. Again, that seems to be like an expression of
intensity of a grief you know you're not looking around for some
scissors, it's like you just you know it's a sense of an
immediacy and intensity. It's really hard with modern clothing. It's really hard
with modern clothing. Yes, we anyway we get people started with a
little cut from a razor. But that's not the whole tearing, that's
just getting it started you know. ואמר רבי חייא. ve'amar Rabbi Chiyya.
It's much more personal when it's with the hands than it's with
some instrument. So ואמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן כל
המתים כולם מבפנים, V'amar Rabbi Chiyya bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan kol
hametim kulam mipnim, all other relatives on the inside, על אביו ועל
אמו קורע מבחוץ, al aviv v'al imo koreiah mibachutz, mother and father
outside. What does this mean? So some say it means you do
it in private the act of קריעה, keriah, the act is public,
the רמב"ן the Ramban says then it wouldn't say מבפנים mibpnim and
מבחוץ, umibachutz, it would have said בפנים bifnim and בחוץ. bachutz. And
he says what it means is whether the קריעה keriah is done
like on the outside, you know, where your hands are? Are they
on the outside of the garments or are they on the inside
tearing out? I don't know, the inside tearing out seems just physically
more difficult. But anyway, either way it does make it more demonstrative
and more public when it's on the outside. אמר רב חסדא Amar
Rav Chisda וכן לנשיא, v'chen l'nasi,
and this echoes back in earlier discussion, how one deals with the
death of a נשיא, nasi, right, the leader of the people, so
that would be similar to אביו ואמו aviv v'imo and a similar
type of a קריעה. keriah. מיתיבי, Metivei, they ask on this says
the גמרא, the Gemara, לא הושוו לאביו ולאמו אלא לאיחוי בלבד. lo
hushvu l'aviv u'l'imo ela l'ichuy bilvad. When they make comparisons about a
נשיא nasi and other people to mother and father, it was only
regarding this issue of sewing up the the the tear. It wasn't
about the act of tearing in other aspects of it. So מאי
לאו mai lav אפילו לנשיא, afilu l'nasi, doesn't it mean that even
a נשיא nasi is not comparable other than in the הלכה halacha
of sewing up the tear? גמרא Gemara says לא, lo, לבר מנשיא,
l'var minasi, no, a נשיא nasi is different. Other types of people
might have certain similarities to אביו ואמו aviv v'imo and not others,
but נשיא nasi is a fuller comparison and even this הלכה halacha
of how the tearing is done would be done similar by a
נשיא. nasi. So now let's just have one story about that. נשיא
שכיב, Nasi shachiv, a נשיא nasi passed away.
אמר ליה רב חסדא Amar leh Rav Chisda to רב נחמן בר
אמי Rav Nachman bar Ami or רב חנן בר רבא, Rav Chanan
bar Rava, כפי
אסיטא, kfi asita, upturn the grinding vessel,
whatever, the mortar, וקומה עלה v'kumah alah and stand on it, meaning
so you have like your soapbox, get stand on a platform, ואחוי
קריעה לעלמא v'achvi keriah l'alma and demonstrate קריעה keriah to everybody. So
maybe you go ahead, do a קריעה, keriah, a נשיא nasi just
died, let everybody see you, stand up on a table, do the
קריעה, keriah, and not only you show people how to do קריעה,
keriah, you show people that they have to do a קריעה, keriah,
okay, because the נשיא nasi died.
על חכם חולץ מימין, Al chacham choletz miyamin, for a sage who
dies one exposes the right shoulder, על אב בית דין משמאל, al
av beit din mishmol, on the head of the בית דין beit
din like a major sage, right, a sage of the whole generation,
one does it one does it on the left, which is interesting,
you would think the left would be less respect, but but somehow
maybe anyway somehow it's seen here that that maybe it makes the
person more disheveled even when the left is is uncovered, I don't
know. על נשיא מכאן ומכאן, Al nasi mikan umikan, by a נשיא
nasi both left and right. השמאל זה כנגד הלב? Hashmol zeh k'neged
halev?
The left is to do with the heart, is over the heart?
What?
That's to do with- No, we're talking about the shoulders. Oh, no,
no, it's חולץ. choletz. We're talking about the shoulder. Oh, oh you
mean it's opposite the heart? Oh, that's interesting. That could be, that
could be. Okay, that's a good point.
תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, חכם שמת, chacham shemet, if a sage dies,
בית מדרשו בטל, beit midrasho batel, then his his ישיבה yeshiva stops
in order to do שבעה. shiva. Do they fully observe שבעה shiva
or do they just- no, that's not clear, but they're not they
don't have the ישיבה yeshiva isn't running as usual. אב בית דין
שמת, Av beit din shemet, if the head of if the head
of like the major sage of the whole city, the whole country
dies, כל בתי מדרשות שבעירו בטלים, kol batei midrashot shebiro betelim, then
the whole city stops their learning when the sage of the city
dies. ונכנסים לבית הכנסת, V'nichnasim l'beit haknesset, they go into the שולן,
shuls, ומשנים את מקומם, u'mshanim et mkomam, and they change their own
place. Now people will say this you know this is what we
know by אבל, avel, don't sit in the same place. But here
the funny thing is everybody is אבלים, avelim, so it's not if
everybody is אבלים, avelim, how does a person demonstrate their different status
vis-a-vis others? So everybody sits in a different
place, okay, היושבים בצפון יושבים בדרום והיושבים בדרום יושבים בצפון, Hayoshvim batzafon
yoshvim badarom v'hayoshvim badarom yoshvim batzafon, etc. Okay. נשיא שמת, Nasi shemet,
and if the נשיא nasi dies who's the head of not just
the city but the country, okay, בתי מדרשות כולם בטלים, batei midrashot
kulam betelim, all the
study halls are בטלים, betelim, not just of the city. ובני הכנסת
נכנסים לבית הכנסת, U'vnei haknesset nichnasim l'beit haknesset, and people from the
שול shul go into the שול, shul, וקורין שבעה, v'korin shiva, and
they read seven עליות, aliyot, okay. Now why what does that mean?
They read seven עליות. aliyot. And ויוצאים v'yotzim and they leave. So
if you look at רבנו גרשום, Rabbeinu Gershom, we'll end with this
for now, בספר תורה ואין מתפללין יחד בבית כנסת אלא כל אחד
ואחד מתפלל בביתו. b'sefer torah v'ein mitpallelin yachad b'veit knesset ela kol
echad v'echad mitpallel b'veito. Right,
the we raised before where is the idea that a person doesn't
leave his or her house during שבעה? shiva? So here, you know,
what does this mean, everybody is sitting שבעה, shiva, so they gather
together to do קריאת התורה. kriat hatorah. Why aren't they gathering together
to דאוון, davven, right? So it says no, that would be inappropriate,
that would be like a communal experience. You're supposed to all be,
you know, like everybody's an אבל, avel, so you don't have these
big communal experiences. So רבנו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom says you're דאוונינג, davvening,
people are דאוונינג davvening in their homes, they're just doing something also
communally, you know, at the same time. It's an interesting balance of
why. It's an interesting balance of why we're trying to do something
communally but not exactly the full דאווענינג davening and so on. We'll
read one more line about this. רבי יהושע בן קרחה אומר Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Korcha omer לא שילכו ויתטיילו בשוק. lo sheyeilchu veyitaylu bashuk.
They don't go and they get, go out and take a little
walking around in the marketplace, אלא יושבין ודומין. ela yoshvin vedomin. Okay,
but they sit and they're silent. So again, public demonstration, it's a
very interesting balance. It's a, it's an אבילות aveilus for the whole
community, sort of like תשעה באב, Tisha B'Av, so the community as,
not as individuals, but as a community, has to demonstrate that they're
an אבל, avel, but on the other hand, part of the whole
אבילות aveilus is being separate from the community. So how do you
do that? So you get together for reading the תורה Torah but
not for דאווענינג. davening. You go to the שול shul but everybody
sits in a different place. So you sort of do things as
community but also in a way that you're not fully coming together
as a fully natural community. You go and you're silent, you don't
talk, you sit and you're, everybody is silent together, thinks about certain
things, so that evokes תשעה באב-like Tisha B'Av things. Okay, so we'll
see more about this in a moment.